and Gutronica 9:41
um which is translated as with the uh
householder
tapusa. So at one time the Buddha was
staying in the land of Malas near the
Malian town named
Uruakapa. Uh once the Buddha robed up in
the morning taking his ball and robe he
entered the town for arms. after the
meal on his return he addressed
venerable Ananda
uh Ananda used to stay right here while
I plunged deep into the great wood for
the day's
abiding. So while Ananda was um alone,
the household at
Tapusa approached him, sat down to one
side and said, "Bantanda, we lay
people who partake in sensuality. We are
lay people who partake in
sensuality. We enjoy sensuality. We are
fond of it and are pleased by
it." To us lay people who partake in
sensuality, who enjoy it, are fond of
it, and are pleased by it. Renunciation
seems like an
abyss. I have heard that in this
teaching and discipline there are very
young bicus whose minds leap at
renunciation. Their minds seeing it as
peaceful are confident, settled and
liberated in it. It is precisely the
renunciation that is dividing line
between the many and the bikers in this
teaching and discipline.
So it's like
um um you can notice here
that not just that the um the difference
in partaking in sensuality and minds
leaping towards renunciation has been
highlighted here. It was also
highlighted by a householder. So he uh
he fully
understood that the main difference as
he said the dividing line between the
many i.e. the outsiders, the lay people,
the other practices, the other
teachings. So the main differences
between the many, the manifold and these
because in this teaching and discipline
is this precisely this
renunciation. So it's not like that
there were no other summoners and
brahins they were
practicing practices and renination to
some extent.
that in this particular way in this
teaching and discipline renunciation
does require knowing uh where to apply
it. So not to just turn into blind
aseticism or the external form worship
or similar and um to then obviously they
would then bring understanding as as
we're going to see further in the suta
which is like why then the mind gets to
see it as peaceful and it's confident
and settled and liberated in it. So the
the lay man understood that the very uh
sensuality so abandoning the sensuality
on the right level is the difference
between everybody else and the Buddhist
teaching because um the dividing line
between many and the bakers it's
precisely this renunciation in regard to
sensuality and sensual
desires. So he could have added here, oh
yes, and giants as well, they they have
all sorts of a or steer practices and
they but they still don't abandon
sensuality. And that was also the
Buddha's point. Saying no to things blindly, not
point. Saying no to things blindly, not
recognizing the the root or the the the
gateway for sensuality and your desires,
it's on the level of your intentions.
And then not cultivating it accordingly
means even if you renounce everything to
the extreme, you're still within the
central domain.
So then it goes further well the the
says okay well let's see the Buddha
about this matter um so as he answers so
we shall remember it
um so together they went to the Buddha
bowed and sat to one side and then the
vendor reported this conversation and
the Buddha said that's exactly how it is
before my awakening when I was still an
unawwakened but uh intent bent on
awakening. I too thought renunciation is
good, seclusion is good. But the mind
chitta didn't see renunciation is
peaceful. Didn't leap at it and he
wasn't confident, settled nor liberated
in it. So the Buddha realized, okay, so
why is this the case? Why do I see on
one level that renunciation is
beneficial, seclusion is
beneficial, but the mind is not leaping
towards it. So he said I thought what is
the cause? What is the reason why my
mind doesn't see renunciation as
peaceful and it doesn't leap at it? It
isn't confident, settled and liberated
in
it. And he realized that he hasn't seen
the peril of sensuality and hasn't
cultivated that. He hasn't he have he hasn't
that. He hasn't he have he hasn't
realized the value of renunciation and
didn't foster it. So that's why the mind
doesn't see renunciation as peaceful and
doesn't leap at it and it isn't
confident and settled and liberated in
it. So this is obviously the kind of the
crucial point um
because um you know he could have said
million of different practices that
could lead you to see uh peril in
sensuality because of which your mind is
not leaping at it but he
didn't. He always highlighted the same
thing not having seen the danger
sufficiently enough. I mean there are
many sutas in Angut as well that keep
repeating that if if the one hasn't seen
the danger uh in it the mind is still
within the domain not free from the
hindrances thus devoid of Janna and
everything else. So as we was going to
see later on when we address the more
specific questions the point is there is
no other way of going about it.
Like nothing can magically reveal
you the peril of
sensuality except pondering, thinking
and trying to understand the extent of
the peril of the
sensuality. So that's what that's what
he said. What is the cause? Well, the
cause is that I haven't seen the peril
of sensuality, haven't cultivated it,
hasn't realized the value. So that's why
the mind is not doesn't see renunciation
as peaceful. Then I thought suppose that
having seen the peril of sensuality I
were to cultivate that to not lose the
context of that to not distract myself
from that to not forget
it. I suppose that having realized the
value of renunciation I were to foster
it. It is possible that seeing it that
seeing it as peaceful my mind would then
leap at renunciation and be confident
settled and liberated. And so after some
time having seen the peril of sensuality
I cultivated that having realized the
value of renunciation I fostered
it. Then seeing it as peaceful my mind
left the annunciation and was confident
settled and liberated in it. Having and
so having thoroughly withdrawn from
sensuality having withdrawn from
unbeneficial phenomena with thinking and
pondering with joy and ease born of that
withdrawal I abided having entered upon
the first Janna. So there was no
middleman there. There was no I was
massaging my breath until the pleasure
overwhelmed me and that brought me to
the Janna and wanted and and took my
mind away from sensuality. And by the
way, this this what what this paragraph
this passage describes it's it's just
found in all the other sutras. Whenever
Janna are described, they're described
as arising on account of the condition
of being thoroughly withdrawn from the
five hindrances. Obviously sensuality
being one of the one of the chief of
them. The point being the Buddha didn't
say, "Oh, through practicing such
concentration or such shortcut or such
management technique, I took myself away
from the sensuality that I that I knew
it was bad, but my mind wasn't listening
to me." No, first I basically
um taught my mind the peril of it. I've
seen it for myself first and foremost.
I've seen the extent of it and that
that's when he says um that he
cultivated it. So one thing is to
understand the peril on the level of
your mano and intellect through
pondering through abandoning of the
wrong views. But another thing is for
that value of that renunciation of
sensuality through seeing the peril to
sink in to sink in down to that wild
animal so that as I said before the wild
animal will then also prefer
renunciation not sensuality. It's not
enough to just counter your moods by uh
a subba or to tell yourself this is not
worthy when you feel attracted. That's
all on the level of your intellect. Yes,
you should be doing it. But don't
confuse that for being the practice of
training the chitta. In order to train
the chitta, the thing needs to sink in.
So that's what it means. Having realized
the value of value of pronunciation, he
fostered it. Basically he maintained it,
he protected it, he clarified it
further, he sustained it until he saw
that his own mind now is leaping towards
it actually wants it and then being that
basically constitutes the withdrawal
from the sensuality not your reasoning
and your intellect simply knowing oh
it's bad thus I'm withdrawn when the
mind doesn't want to do it you feel
relieved now because that that implicit
as as other sut say that intimate friend
that always kind
of has potential to send you or or cause
you the danger to your life that's gone
now because he wants the same thing as
you yourself have understood is
beneficial then it's the first
Janna one and only way there is no other
way to
Janna through withdrawal and the
withdrawal is only possible on account
of seeing the
peril otherwise the Buddha wouldn't have
said that very
thing. So he abided in the first John
says as I abide in their way perceptions
and attentions connected with sensuality
beseted me and that was an affliction
for me. Suppose unease would arise for
someone who is at ease. That would be an
affliction for them. In the same way
perceptions and attentions connected
with sensuality besetted me. So that was
in the first
Janna. So withdrawn from the first Janna
surmounting the domain the entire domain
of sensuality. what you're going to have
in front so to speak will be uh
attentions and perceptions that come
from that central
domain. So you'll be withdrawn. There is
the ease of safety, the pleasure, the
joy on account of safety. But the fact
is those things are
there still in front and then he would
realize oh this is not well not as
peaceful as it could be and that's
exactly why he then went to the second
Janna. So in other words, the joy of the
first Janna, the withdrawal, the
absolute wholesomeness, as the other
sutas say, there is nothing unh
wholesome that um that's sort of
uh implicit in the first genre. It's
fully divorced from everything unh
wholesome, but at the arms length there
is still that annoying afflicting
central domain. So you're not directly afflicted
domain. So you're not directly afflicted
of it by it, but it's there in front of
you. And he says those perceptions beset
the mind through thinking and pondering
pretty much. So that's why he thought
how about I appease or I surmount the
thinking and pondering. How about I
withdraw even further? In the same
sense, he realized the peril, the
danger, the
dissatisfaction on that level of his
mano, on that mental level, on the level
of understanding and the view and then
cultivated it, fostered it, thought
about it, contemplated, uh, contemplated
it, meditated it until it sank in, sank,
sank down, sank in into his chitta. So
the chitta turned away from it. How
about he repeats the same regards
thinking and pondering as unbeneficial
as dangerous as perilous as not peaceful
enough until the chitta turns away from
that and it repeats the same the same
formula he said why don't I appease the
thinking and abide in a higher basically
surmounting higher comprehension says
but my mind did not see the absence of
thinking as
peaceful in the same sense it didn't see
before renunciation i.e. the absence of
sensuality didn't see it as peaceful. He
was actually afraid of it. He was
actually uh apprehensive about it,
doubtful all sorts of ways, but he
wasn't seeing it as peaceful. So, you
can't just tell it. You need to teach
it. You need to keep showing it through
your own example. That's why again the
virtue sense restraint is already the
example you're setting for your
chitta. And this is by the way the most
accurate, the most uh direct practice to
the development of Janna. There is no no
clearer method than
this. Through clear pondering, thorough
thorough understanding of the uh danger,
the peril of sensuality, the mind will
leap towards renunciation. It will lean
away. It will turn away from sensual
desires. But not who knows how that how
long that will
take because again different people
carried like you know different uh
depths of their desires to put it that
way. So some people might will need
longer some people not but the point is
you won't be able to be conveying the
message of the peril the danger of
sensuality if you're still not withdrawn
even through your physical behavior and
verbal behavior and the coarse mental
thoughts and so on of indulgence. So
that all that's all practice of Janna
basically from the day one to the actual
Janna if you're doing it rightly you are
practicing the Janna at any given moment
of
it. So then the Buddha realized that he
again needs to repeat the same type of
uh development of the context for his
mind so that the mind starts to u see
the absence of thinking as
peaceful. And then he repeats the same
and says on a later occasion basically
he abided in this way and then
um he recognized that perception
attentions connected with uh with
thinking besetted him of of that
sensuality and there was an affliction.
So suppose an unease will arise for
someone who is at ease and then um he
realized that okay so now that the
absence of
thinking he developed he wasn't bothered
by the perceptions of sensuality like
before but now in the second Janna he
realized that becomes bothersome again
it's it's not bothersome in a sense that
um you know in a sense that sensuality
is perilous and bothersome you know says
that first Janna is enough to become an
arant if you if you stay in it long
enough in a sense of and I don't mean
like a momentary hypnotic concentration
or absorption or something means if you
cultivate that context whereby instead
of sensual desires what you're bothered
is thinking and pondering of the
perceptions of sensuality while you're
fully withdrawn from it you stay long
enough in in that uh in that setup in
that context you will be free from
sensuality eventually but obviously the
Buddha you know trying to find the
ultimate way out the complete way out
having leaving nothing unturned he
realized okay so is there higher than
this so is there higher than the second
Janna
now and realized that the way to get
higher was also to recognize now that
the absence of thinking the absence of
sensual perceptions and thoughts that
were beset him uh well that that too
actually could be even more pleasant and
from that point of view as in more
pleasant more agreeable more beneficial
And from that point of view you he
referred to it as an
affliction. Um so then he thought why
don't I with a fading away of joy
abiding economous recollected
comprehending experiencing ease with the
body abide having entered upon the third
Janna with regard to which the noble one
say one abides economous recollected and
at ease. But again the mind didn't see
the absence of that joy of second Janna
when the thinking and pondering has been
stilled. hasn't seen the joy of that as
peaceful. So after some time having seen
the peril of that joy the implicit risk
he cultivated it having realized the
value of the absence of joy he fostered
that seeing it as peaceful the mind
started leaping towards
that and then he was abiding having
entered upon the third
Janna having abided in that way
perceptions and attentions connected
with the
joy started to beset him he realized the
affliction that's an affliction and then
repeats the same process why don't I
with a giving up of ease and unease and
with the ending of those joys and
upsets surmount that domain and with
purity of equinimity and recollection
without ease or unease abide having
entered upon the fourth
Janna and it repeats the same after the
fourth Janna how about I surmount all
the perceptions of resistance but the
mind doesn't see the extent of infinite
space as
peaceful so he first comprehended the
extent of infinite face uh cultivated
it, abandoned
any residual views that that would have
been uh preventing basically from him to
to to for himself on the level of his
mano to realize that is peaceful and
once that was all
clear doubtfree protected that context
until it sank in down to that animal
which then also agreed and realized oh
no this is indeed peaceful and leapt at
it that's when he enter Janna or enter
second Janna or third or fourth or
infinite space. So then he went further because
space. So then he went further because
he could see that well he could still
continue surmounting whatever is in
front of him. So why don't I having
fully surmounted the extent of infinite
space aware that consciousness is
infinite abide having entered
that my mind didn't see the extent of it
initially later on he did so he entered
it then he thought why don't I having
fully surmounted the extent of infinite
consciousness aware that there is
nothing so the pretty much the the the
domain the extent of nothingness
um taught his mind how to how to see it
as peaceful leapt at
entered it. Why don't I having fully
surmounted the extent of nothingness
abide having entered upon the extent of
neither perception or perception? same
until it sank in he couldn't but then
when the mind fully understood the
chitta fully understood that it is
actually beneficial and then he leapt
towards it and then uh um after a while
he realized that perceptions and
attentions connected with that extent of
nothingness are basically
bothersome. So he thought is there
higher than this and he realized yes
there is higher which is sensation of
perception and feeling after some time
surmounted the same the mind leapt
towards sensation of perception of
feeling and he he basically was abiding
in it and that's when he realized that
that's it there is absolutely nothing
that can be um underlied by influxes
from this point onwards. So if somebody
were to progressively develop all the
way to the sensation of perception and
feeling there is no like only now you
have to spend time in it so to speak
because if you come to that point there
would be no more influxes left
underneath you so to speak in the first
Janna there still could be second Janna
there still could be that's why he said
he did not claim his full
enlightenment oh yeah it's the next
paragraph as long as I hadn't entered
upon withdrawn from these nine
progressive attainments of abiding in
both forward and reverse order. I did
not announce my supreme perfect
awakening in this world with its god
maras and
brahas. This population with aesthetics
and brahinss it god and humans. But when
he has entered upon and withdrawn fully
understood u this this the withdrawal
principle on account of seeing the
danger mind also accepting it leaping
towards the the higher domain. Then he
did announce that his liberation of the
mind is unshakable last birth. There is
absolutely nothing that can underly it.
No um as anas like how they're known in
other
sutas. So yeah um you know a few obvious
questions come up on the basis of this
suta like putting aside the um the
subtler attainments they just follow the
same principle also you know you can
wrap your head around say u the base of
infinite space and um consciousness is
infinite and and so
on but if you haven't actually at least
withdrawn yourself from sensuality into
a first Janna
It's it's it's pointless to even try to
figure out those higher states because
it won't be those states you're figuring
out. Um so if we go back to the very
first one which is sensuality is an abyss.
one which is sensuality is an abyss.
um how do you basically uh overcome that
abyss and find the safety that's
completely not dependent on the body or
the flesh how the sutras would say i.e.
the five senses. So it's completely
withdrawn from it. There is no no point
of contact with it. no dependence on any
other uh you know slightly slightly
better sense object or similar but it's
truly withdrawn truly safe truly
unshakable from that point of view which
is what the first Janna is so the
question is like then can even a
householder is there a way for him to uh
not experience renunciation as an
abyss and um of course yes Initially
when you think about what if if a
householder would think about it's going
to be um well scary that's kind of the
um the inevitable say outcome. Somebody
who hasn't practiced any restraint
hasn't heard about the necessity of the
virtue and restraint or heard it like on
the level of oh this is something
optional or
um conditional I could I could do it you
know sometimes but it's not it's not the
core of the practice. It's not like the
direction of the Janna. When they hear
that they have to do it, yeah, they'll
they're going to be upset uh because
they're going to blame everybody else
except their own sensual desires that do
define that abyss because that's another
thing. By the way, the abyss of of
sensuality is not defined because it's
actually or factually they're an abyss.
It's defined by the strength of your
desires towards those sense
objects. So the stronger your desires,
the bigger the abyss if you were to even
consider saying no to them.
uh but there's no other way around it.
As I said, there is no magical formula
or potion. They will just do it for you.
So is there a way for householder to
eventually not experience that is abyss?
Absolutely. Gradual training in virtue,
restraining um recognizing the the that that that
um recognizing the the that that that
that level as we as we speak about with
your intentions that are rooted in
greed, aversion,
distraction, taming that, not acting out
of that. Um that's all of that is
already shrinking the
abyss. Um but see in order to do that
you already you you do need like on the
level of your mana on the level of your
intellect you need to start actually
ponder and think think about it
because it's like going against your
entire existence the grain of your
existence. So you're going to need to
have a pretty good reason to do it. And
unless you would have really like sat
down with it repeatedly, contemplated it
and so on, no amount of reasons will
will sink in to to that
cheitt as as afraid of that abyss as it
is initially when you present it with
it. So for that you do need to basically
even tailor your environment. stop
seeking uh mindless distraction and
safety in the distraction through the
environment. Um so all that needs to be
be reigned in honed in and then uh
protected maintained and then the
cheetah gets used to it and then you
bring it closer and then chitta gets
used to it. You don't do it overnight
for sure. But the worst danger is to
have the view that you don't have to do
it. And you know many people do have
that view. Even people that keep the
virtue, they keep it in that as I said
conditional sense. I keep it because
somebody said it supports my my uh
meditation concentration um
self-hypnotic practice. So that's why
I'm keeping it. But I don't keep it as a
form of I'm actually training my chitta
in this. I'm recognize my intentions,
taking responsibility for it. So you're
not really keeping
it. Um so initially when somebody says
no to their desires and they haven't
done it before or haven't done it
seriously well that abyss will probably
even become
bigger because again the mind the
cheater will panic and it will try to to
pressure you through fear and doubt to
actually don't do it and go back to it.
But as I said like there is absolutely
no other way. And that's even what this
householder realized. Tapusa he said oh
this is the very thing that
differentiates everybody else from this
teaching and
discipline. Um so the sooner you start
the better
really. Um so yeah so kind of the next
natural question would be uh what would
be the more specific practical things
that a person who
now wants to train in this what can they
do so that that cha will eventually that
wild animal will eventually leap towards
renunciation itself and um as we said virtue and
itself and um as we said virtue and
restraint not negotiable but it's
important to to start emphasizing the
right things not all at once just say no
to everything and just lock yourself in
the room and no distractions.
Like that's you could say by some
stretch of theory if somebody really
knows what they're doing that could
possibly work but practically speaking
you're going to overwhelm that chitter.
So take on the
precepts, five precepts with celibacy.
Work towards it, but at the same time,
yeah, don't neglect the sense of urgency
in regard to it because you might not
have your whole life ahead of you. Well,
actually, you always have your whole
life ahead of you. It's just that that
whole life might not last as long as you
hope it
will. So um emphasizing the important
the the you know the core convergence
point of sensuality the big things and
training in regard to that and then
refining it as the time passes as the
chitta becomes more comfortable and so
on. Not all at once thinking if I just
adhere to this blindly as a form of
aesthetic practice pretty much the
chitta will magically become
enlightened. No, no. Understanding needs
to be born out of your virtue and
restraint. And no amount of willpower
will just magically create
understanding. So in order to do that,
you need to start prioritizing the right
thing. As I said already, you got to pay
attention to your environment and tailor
it to the extent that you can so that
that that you know your chitta and your
senses are not simply
overwhelmed overwhelmed and bombarded
with too many things that that you just
can't cope
with. So,
um sorting out your
priorities. Um, oh yeah, so one of you
sent this in in in an email as a reply
and I thought I'll just read it out
because it's was a good list, good
checklist. So what a lay person should
aim at doing is sorting out the
priorities which uh will certainly going
to cause some hustle
um hassle hassle in the beginning due to
doubt, uncertainty, fear, attachments,
obligations and so on. But you have to
recognize okay my work begins with this
um pondering around the question what
comes first in your priorities. So is it
is it more important to be liberated
from sensuality and free from samsara
once and for all or your lay life
satisfactions and joys. It's a it's a
it's a kind of simple choice really.
It's not complex but it's not going to
be an easy choice to make because
although even as the Buddha said on the
mental level he understood that no actually
level he understood that no actually
renunciation is good seclusion is is is
excellent but the cheetah was like no no
I I disagree with that I want this
um so in order to then train it as the
next checklist says you got to establish
the faith basically establish the faith
in these teachings in a sense of to
start applying it you're not going have
an immediate verification that sense
restraint is good and seclusion is good
but if you reason uh clearly enough like
you don't need some high intellect to
understand these principles you just
need some um honesty basically you would
see that well it's certainly worth a try
but if you decide to try then you have
to have faith that like okay I got to
try this really and properly not
half-heartedly so faith in the
application of uh quite a
straightforward non-intellectual distri
uh instruction of training in virtue and
precepts and sense
restraint. Yeah, that's that's like a
pretty much the necessary condition for
somebody to start doing
it. So, got to read the
sutras, remind yourself, learn about
different aspects of renunciation,
clarify it as possible so that you can
actually be
practicing. Um the next checklist is
well accordingly you have to be then
associating with the people of the same
values. seek their advice if you're in a
position to do so and follow
it. Practice d and generosity and of
course um be uh aim towards celibacy if
you're not already celibate and uh and
include that because that's like one of
the main um exemplification of the
entire central domain. So
um then later on say you you know you're
celibate you're restrained uh you could
then start discerning the subtler layers
of the five hindrances and how they
manifest in different ways. Um I mean
you could start thinking about it even
now but first things
but first things
first. Um so all of that obviously is
predicated on watching your actions by
body, speech and
mind behavior um as we spoke before not
allowing the center stage and so on um
on the basis of withdrawal and and from
the unh wholesome states and and further
and that's how the mind will eventually
also dry up from those uh from those
desires and that's that's pretty much
the time when you would start seeing
your own chitta actually preferring it
actually leaping towards it.
So as it was said already um the only
way out of this it's not through as I
said um physical sensations meditation
um physical sensations meditation
techniques astral projections
visualizations or whatever your practice
of meditation might be is through one
and only path of fully seeing the danger
of the central domain that you're living
in. So if the Buddha himself with the
greatest parameies and everything could
not do it any other way I would be
probably as I said you don't even need a
great intellect and reasoning to see
that okay so then if he couldn't do it
who am I to talk about doing some some
other way quicker way or or or a
different type of J way like that's mean
like if you're honest you realize okay
so if he laid it out and again it's Not
it's not hard to
understand. It's just hard to stick to
it because people would like faith in
application and then you know choose
pretty much every other excuse to
dismiss the application or the the
speaker who gave them that application
or the sutas or the Buddha and do what
they want to do which is basically stay
in the central domain because they don't
want to develop and face the abyss.
So that's again I mean I've been already
mentioning it but it's it's it's good to
say it clearly. So like when you know
question so could somebody still
hypothetically practice
concentration you know the way it's um
being uh taught uh to today. Can they
practice concentration to encourage you
know to to speed up to speed up the the
leaping of the chitta towards the
renunciation faster? And it's an obvious
categorical absolutely no because
whatever you are concentrating will be
the object of your own mano and it won't
be the chitta behind it. So if there
would be a
um magical object that can take the you
know the chitta in the background the
animal that you're not even seeing
towards renunciation well the Buddha
would have outlined it.
So the closer to the object of your
concentration you can get is the object
of your thoughts of thinking and
pondering about the peril of
sensuality. If people try and argue and
say well you know the the physical
sensations are not sensual how can they
not be sensual if they come from your
body which is one giant field of touch.
Does it matter how you try to spin it or
breath is not sensual. Is it felt in the
body? Yes. I mean even the suta say
breath is inseparable from the body.
It's bodily. That's why it's
ka. If it's connected with your body
it's connected with the flesh. There is
no other way around it. If people say
well it doesn't harm anybody. Well lots
of things don't harm anybody.
Self-pleasuring doesn't harm anybody
technically. Yet we all know how unh
wholesome that would be from somebody
who wants to be celibate and keep the
precepts. So it's just as I said if
you're honest you will see that the
reasoning in defending sensations or or
breath meditations of pleasure they will
take your mind away from it doesn't hold
up and when when the Buddha did teach
aanasati it was on the level of
understanding and using the breath to
outline your own body uh from which you
are pretty much already thoroughly or
sufficiently withdrawn instead of concentrating
withdrawn instead of concentrating
instead of um anisticizing yourself
basically through the common practices
of
meditation. Invest the effort in calming
down your environment, calming down your
engagements with it, calming down the
pulls and pressures that you experience
on account of it. Go and sit down
quietly, but not out of that duty that
as a Buddhist I must do this
concentration because otherwise I feel
like I don't know what I'm doing. and
sit down quietly and then think and
ponder to the full extent of why
sensuality is dangerous and why your own
mind doesn't want to turn away from
it and do it pretty much until the mind
turns away from it and that would be
your Janna. So the only way to encourage your
Janna. So the only way to encourage your
chitta to turn the wild animal to turn
towards renunciation is that you
yourself fully understand the benefit of
it. So that's why I said the first
reason your cheat the cheat is not
turning towards it is because you
yourself have not clarified and and
understood the benefits for yourself on
the level of your own mind mano on the
level of your own or your own intellect.
Um
so yeah so let's say somebody does
develop that householder perfectly
perfectly possible if if he's celibate
and withdrawn and he enters the first
Janna then as other householders in the
sutas existed became skilled in all four
Janas because following the same
progression and also you know once on
say like you abandoned the central
domain yes it would require that
diligence of bringing up the context of
the peril of the thinking and pondering
of the first Janna that's being beseted
by the perceptions of sensuality and so
on. Uh but it it won't be as much of a
chore as it was overcoming the
abyss. So that's why like you know the
the faith would would have already been
thoroughly confirmed by then. So once
you once somebody's in the first Janna
they can easily continue practicing the
same thing uh and get even closer to
that full enlightenment and removal of
all the underlying tendencies and so on.
So the principle between that
progression I already described it
through the uh when we read the suta and
it's the one you can say you progress
upwards only through suranting what's in
front. So there is absolutely no other
other way to it or other shortcut or
similar. So this might bring up an idea
of like you know the foreground and the
peripheral in your
mind and theoretically that is true but
practically foreground and the
peripheral say when you think about it
will always carry an implicit intention
there and then for you that would be
implying that I must
surmount the foreground by including all
the peripheral
And that intention needs to be
included. But see that's not something
you can just attend as a foreground. So
yes, foreground and the peripheral
whatever that is at whatever stage you
might be. And then recognize your the
implicit imperative in it. I must
surmount this and include it not follow
it to surmount it to surmount for
peripheral because then you're still
acting out of hindrance.
Uh but obviously a lot more can be said
about that. Maybe we can do another
another suta reading. Um so yeah
somebody asked would it be correct to
say that the mind cannot understand the
chitta cannot understand the peril of a
less wholesome state and the value in a
more wholesome state without being
actually fully thoroughly first
withdrawn from the less unh wholesome
state. And yes yes that's absolutely
correct. And that withdrawal is the uh
necessary basis for actual successful and and and
basis for actual successful and and and
and productive understanding and
contemplation of oh sensuality is bad or
or like oh yeah thinking and pondering
is a nuisance from the point of view of
the second Janna. So first you need to
withdraw yourself from
sensuality physically. stop giving into
it in order that you first be able to
understand how it's not beneficial and
how it's perilous in order for then that
knowledge to sink down to the
chitta. Um, as we said
before, you can't contemplate the peril
of sensuality unless you're first
withdrawn from sensuality. is just going
to stay on a completely abstract level
and it can actually lead you astray even
more because while engaging with
sensuality you think you're
contemplating the the peril and in other
words that which could have actually
served as a peril becomes something
you're attracted to now because you've
been acting towards it while you were
thinking thinking the uh assuba thoughts
and so on. So, so the peril is on the
level of
uh the core of sensuality, the core of
giving into those desires of that wild
animal is what keeps the wild animal
wild. And any pain you would have
experienced, any pain you will
experience, any pain that you could
imagine you could experience, any
suffering basically any pain, I mean any
dooka, that is the sole reason for it.
It's the wilderness of that animal I
craving. It's not the circumstances. It's not the
It's not the circumstances. It's not the
highway robbers chopping your limbs.
It's not losing the loved ones.
It's the sole thing is the wilderness of
that animal. And uh once you are very clear
animal. And uh once you are very clear
about that, the abyss will disappear.
Sure, you might still get careless as
some of the noble disciples did in the
sutas because the abyss has disappeared
because to that extent the animal has
seen oh that's where all the problems
come from. Um you chase after sensuality
you protect what's yours so to
experience that peace that peace which
always is undermined by your very chase
by the very pressure towards the chase
by the craving behind
it. So that's like the most direct thing
um direct principle behind the peril of
sensuality that you can see. But as I
said one thing is you you hear this you
think about it you make sense of it and
another thing is to actually start doing
it. So
um in order to to to
[Music] discern the domain of
discern the domain of
sensuality in order for mind to leap
away from it, you need to not
just stop uh giving in to the
contradictory acts of of of following
your desires or real will and so on. You
also have to stop
resisting what comes up when you when
you sort of restrain your mind. When you
when you round up, when you say no to
desires, the pressures, the abyss that
come up, you have to stop resisting it
as well in a sense of you have to stop
being averse towards it
because again that keeps you connected
to
it. So that's why the the the whole
non-resistance towards foreground and
peripheral and the intention to act out
of it needs to be thoroughly developed.
But see that non-resistance that we talk
about enduring on the right level we
talk about uh which fosters that
resistance that can only be done once
you round up the mind once you actually
do have some aggregate of virtue and
sense restraint because you know if you
don't saying oh I won't resist anything
basically almost automatically means oh
you go back to sensuality no you got to
resist things because the initial
starting point is too much of of
basically flowing going along with the flow. So
flowing going along with the flow. So
you got to resist the flow. You got to
resist the cover the
current and then the result of that okay
now I should not resist that and that's
how you find the middle way the balance
so to speak.
Um so and then yes somebody also asked
like so you know technically speaking
one could leave the household life
today become a monk give up you know the
the household life belongings family and
so on but not necessarily renounce
sensuality on the level of their
desires. Exactly. or still resisted and
think that just through doubling down in
the resistance in aesthetic practices
and following the the the sense of duty
or whatever else they will they will
just power through it. It's like no. So
even if somebody say technically
somebody could be a monk would have been
or a nun given up household life given
up family and still very
much remain connected to sensuality
which means still very much be exposed
to that
abyss because it still hasn't been been
addressed. Uh the mind still hasn't been
trained to get used to it. Stop fearing
it. Stop stop being anxious in the face
of it.
uh and then uh it's always going to be
there as a potential. So even if you
never experience abyss, it's because you
never said no to those desires on that
level or because you're an arand. So
which which one of those two is? Well,
you can
guess pretty much covers the basic
principles of this suta. As I said, I
didn't want to go
into neither perceptions nor perceptions
and so on and just just inate you with
with theoretical ideas and knowledges.
while the the most practical principle
that sits right in front of your face
could be developed with the actual
fruits and the benefit of it. Um, so
that's why I chose to to stick to that.